Guide to the Edward Knoblock papers, 1904-1936 MS 324
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Edward Knoblock papers
1904-1936
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Knoblock, Edward, 1874-1945
MS 324
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Playwright, scenarist and novelist, Edward Knoblock (1874-1945) was born in New York City and educated at Harvard, but spent most of his professional life living and working in Great Britain. The Knoblock papers are comprised of correspondence received by Knoblock between the years 1904 and 1936, relating to theater in Great Britain during the early 20th century. Most of Knoblock's correspondents in this collection are well-known literary figures of the day, or prominent managers and producers from the world of the theatre, including Sir William Nicholson (1872-1949).
Biographical Note
Edward Knoblock (1874-1945) was born in New York City and educated at Harvard, but spent most of his professional life living and working in Great Britain. Playwright, scenarist and novelist, Knoblock was in constant touch with many of the leading literary and artistic figures of his generation, as the ensuing collection will show. As well as working independently, Knoblock often collaborated with others. The plays, Milestones (1912), and, London Life (1924) were produced with the assistance of Arnold Bennett. Similarly, The Good Companions, originally published in 1929 by J.B. Priestley, was dramatised jointly by Knoblock and the author in 1931. Plays written by Knoblock alone include, The Faun (1911), Kismet (1911), My Lady's Dress (1914), Marie-Odile (1915), and Tiger-Tiger (1918). Among the novels written by Edward Knoblock are, The Ant Heap (1929), The Man With Two Mirrors(1931), The Love Lady (1933), and Inexperience (1941). Some of these works are referred to throughout the collection, notably by Dame Edith Sitwell and David Belasco.
Scope and Contents
The Edward Knoblock collection comprises 45 folders of correspondence received by Knoblock between the years 1904 and 1936, relating to theater in Great Britain during the early 20th century. Correspondence relates to British theater in the early 20th century.
Most of Knoblock's correspondents in this collection are well-known literary figures of the day, or prominent managers and producers from the world of the theatre. Some of these are: Sir Arthur Wing Pinero (1855-1934), the English dramatist and actor; J.B. Priestley (1894- ), the Yorkshire born novelist, essayist, playwright and critic; all the members of the literary Sitwell family, especially, Edith (1887-1964), Osbert (1892-1969), and Sacheverell (1897- ); Sir Hugh Walpole (1884-1941) the New Zealand born novelist and son of the bishop of Edinburgh; Sir Charles Wyndham (1863-1913), the English actor and stage manager; David Belasco (1854-1931), the San Francisco born New York stage manager and producer; Arnold Bennett (1867-1931), the famous English novelist and dramatist of the 'Five Towns' region; Noel Coward (1899- ), the playwright, actor, and composer; English actors, Sir John Gielgud, born in 1904, and Sir Charles Hawtrey (1858-1923); statesman, and first Labour Prime Minister, Ramsey MacDonald (1866-1937); novelist, journalist, and critic, Compton MacKenzie (1883- ); and, Cyril Maude (1863-1951), the English actor, co-manager of the Haymarket theatre in London (1896-1905) and manager and builder of the Playhouse until 1915.
Owing to the volume of correspondence from him contained in the collection, Sir William Nicholson (1872-1949) deserves a special mention. Nicholson was principally a portrait painter, although he also devoted time to painting figure subjects, still life and open-air studies. He was also a wood engraver and designed posters along with his brother-in-law James Pryde under the name of the Beggarshot Brothers. A series of woodcuts were published including, The Square Book of Animals (1896), and An Almanac of Twelve Sports (1898), this latter being produced in collaboration with Rudyard Kipling. Most of Nicholson's letters to Knoblock are accompanied by small illustrations of some kind, and the collection concludes with ten miscellaneous sketches by this artist.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased 1955 through Friends of Fondren.
General
The abbreviations used in the following description of the collection are defined as:
ALS: Handwritten signed letter.
TLS: Typed signed letter.
AC: Handwritten card.
Index Terms
Subjects
Theater; English drama -- 20th century; Theatrical productions; Playwriting; Literature
Document Types
sketchbooks; corrrespondence
Subjects (Persons)
Priestley, J. B. (John Boynton), 1894-1984; Sitwell, Edith, Dame, 1887-1964; Walpole, Hugh, Sir, 1884-1941; Wyndham, Charles, 1837-1919; Mackenzie, Compton, Sir, 1883-1972; Maude, Cyril, 1862-1951; Nicholson, William, Sir, 1872-1949; Pinero, Arthur Wing, 1855-1934; Bennett, Arnold, 1867-1931; Belasco, David, 1853-1931; Hawtrey, Charles, 1858-1923; Gielgud, John, 1904-2000; Coward, Noel, 1899-1973
- Series I. Correspondence, 215362
  - Sir George Alexander to Edward Knoblock, 1912-03-05-1919-02-05 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - AC Sir George Alexander to Edward Knoblock An expression of thanks., 1919-02-05; 215423
    - ALS Sir George Alexander to Edward Knoblock Invitation to be a guest at the annual dinner of a theatrical fund., 1912-03-05; 215422
  - William Archer to Edward Knoblock, 1908-10-06 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ALS William Archer to Edward Knoblock Agreeing to attend the rehearsals., 1908-10-06; 215421
  - Enid Bagnold to Edward Knoblock, 1918-02-24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ALS Enid Bagnold to Edward Knoblock Praising and discussion some of Knoblock's poems., 1918-02-24; 215420
  - Squire Bancroft to Edward Knoblock, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS Squire Bancroft to Edward Knoblock Saying he had made use of Knoblock's name, privately., 1914-06-09; 215419
    - ALS Squire Bancroft to Edward Knoblock Acknowledgement of a gift to the Academy of Dramatic Art., 1914-10-01; 215418
  - David Belasco to Edward Knoblock, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - TLS David Belasco to Edward Knoblock Praising him for his play, 1918-07-10; 215417
    - TLS David Belasco to Edward Knoblock Saying how well is progressing, and asking for more., 1919-03-25; 215416
    - TLS David Belasco to Edward Knoblock Saying he is glad Knoblock is out of the war and is looking forward to receiving a new Ms., 1919-05-29; 215415
    - TLS David Belasco to Edward Knoblock Writing about Knoblock's new play, 18 July 1919; 215414
    - TLS David Belasco to Edward Knoblock Telling of the progress of on tour., 1919-10-06; 215413
    - TLS David Belasco to Edward Knoblock Asking Knoblock to write some verse for framing. This series from Belasco also contains a flier about a life of David Belasco by a William Winter., 1919-12-01; 215412
  - ? to Edward Knoblock, 1917-10-12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - AC ? to Edward Knoblock A note of thanks., 1917-10-12; 215411
  - Arnold Bennett to Edward Knoblock, 1918-07-12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS Arnold Bennett to Edward Knoblock Asking Knoblock if he would like to be a secretary of a new entertainment-of -foreigners committee which is being formed., 1918-07-12; 215410
  - Irving Berlin to Edward Knoblock, 1926-12-04 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - TLS Irving Berlin to Edward Knoblock Thanks for a wire and hoping for a visit., 1926-12-04; 215409
  - Louis Bromfield to Edward Knoblock (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Undated, ALS Louis Bromfield to Edward Knoblock Saying he will be coming to London., 215408
    - Undated, ALS Louis Bromfield to Edward Knoblock About Knoblock's request for French lodgings for a freind of his., 215407
  - Sir Charles Cochran to Edward Knoblock, 1920-1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Undated, ALS Sir Charles Cochran to Edward Knoblock Congratulaing Knoblock on producing a new play and offering his criticisms., 215406
    - Undated, ALS Sir Charles Cochran to Edward Knoblock Hoping to negotiate a West End opening with Douglas Fairbanks and Robin Hood., 215405
    - ALS Sir Charles Cochran to Edward Knoblock Thanks, and asking him to use his first name and not the formal mode of address., 1920-08-20; 215404
    - ALS Sir Charles Cochran to Edward Knoblock Asking for a lunch date., 1922-10-22; 215403
    - ALS Sir Charles Cochran to Edward Knoblock Glad to hear Knoblock can come up to London for rehearsals., 1924-05-31; 215402
    - ALS Sir Charles Cochran to Edward Knoblock Letter from the Kurhaus Hoven - a sanatorium/ convalescence home., 1935-08; 215401
    - ALS Sir Charles Cochran to Edward Knoblock Letter from Freiburg, 1935-07-23; 215400
    - ALS Sir Charles Cochran to Edward Knoblock Letter from Konstanz/Bodensee., 1935-08-09; 215399
    - ALS Sir Charles Cochran to Edwards Knoblock Letter from Freiburg., 1935-08; 215398
  - Noel Coward to Edward Knoblock, 1928-1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - ALS Noel Coward to Edward Knoblock, 1928-03-29; 215397
    - ALS Noel Coward to Edward Knoblock, 1929-04-10; 215396
    - ALS Noel Coward to Edward Knoblock, 1931-05-22; 215395
    - ALS Noel Coward to Edward Knoblock, 1933-09-21; 215394
    - ALS Noel Coward to Edward Knoblock, 1933-09-29; 215393
  - Edith Craig to Edward Knoblock (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Undated, ALS Edith Craig to Edward Knoblock Discussing a children's performance of The Old Woman I'm the Shoe., 215392
  - Clemence Dane to Edward Knoblock (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Undated, ALS Clemence Dane to Edward Knoblock Thanking him for a gift and hoping they can meet soon., 215391
  - Ruth D. to Edward Knoblock (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - ALS Ruth D(raper) ? to Edward Knoblock, 215390
  - Eddy Dennis to Edward Knoblock, 1920-12-28 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - TLS Eddy ? Dennis to Edward Knoblock Everything is much the same in London; the usual parties, the usual gang. I don't go to any of them., 1920-12-28; 215389
  - Lynn Fontanne to Edward Knoblock (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Undated, ALS Lynn Fontanne to Edward Knoblock, 215388
  - St. John Simms to Edward Knoblock, 1928-06-25 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - TLS St John Simms to Edward Knoblock Trying to arrange a time to meet., 1928-06-25; 215387
  - John Gielgud to Edward Knoblock (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Undated, ALS ? (John Geilgud) to Edward Knoblock, 215386
  - Helen Granville Barker to Edward Knoblock, 1920-1925, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Undated, ALS Helen Granville Barker to Edward Knoblock, 215385
    - Undated, ALS Helen Granville Barker to Edward Knoblock, 215384
    - Undated, ALS Helen Granville Barker to Edward Knoblock, 215383
    - ALS Helen Granville Barker to Edward Knoblock, 1920-11-02; 215382
    - ALS Helen Granville Barker to Edward Knoblock, 1922-07-12; 215381
    - ALS Helen Granville Barker to Edward Knoblock, 1925-02-01; 215380
  - Yvette Guilbert to Edward Knoblock, 1919, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Undated, C Yvette Guilbert to Edward Knoblock, 215379
    - Undated, C Yvette Guilbert to Edward Knoblock, 215378
    - Undated, ALS Yvette Guilbert to Edward Knoblock, 215377
    - Undated, ALS Yvette Guilbert to Edward Knoblock, 215376
    - Undated, ALS Yvette Guilbert to Edward Knoblock, 215375
    - ALS Yvette Guilbert to Edward Knoblock, 1919-05-19; 215374
  - Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 1912-1920, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Undated, ALS Sacha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 215373
    - Undated, ALS Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 215372
    - Undated, ALS Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 215371
    - Undated, ALS Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 215370
    - Undated, ALS Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 215369
    - Undated, C Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 215368
    - Undated, ALS Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 215367
    - ALS Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 1912-08-11; 215366
    - ALS Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 1912-12-12; 215365
    - C Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 1912-10-12; 215364
    - ALS Sasha Guitry to Edward Knoblock, 1920-06-14; 215363
  - Sir Charles Hawtrey to Edward Knoblock, 1919, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - ALS Sir Charles Hawtrey to Edward Knoblock, 215361
    - TLS Sir Charles Hawtrey to Edward Knoblock, 1919-12-22; 215360
  - Anita Loos to Edward Knoblock (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Undated, ALS Anita Loos to Edward Knoblock, 215359
  - E.V. Lucas to Edward Knoblock, 1919-1934, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - ALS E.V. Lucas to Edward Knoblock, 215358
    - ALS E.V. Lucas to Edward Knoblock, 1919-11-06; 215357
    - ALS E.V. Lucas to Edward Knoblock, 1934-06-03; 215356
    - ALS E.V. Lucas to Edward Knoblock, 1934-07-16; 215355
    - ALS E.V. Lucas to Edward Knoblock, 1934-06-18; 215354
  - Sir Edward Lutyens to Edward Knoblock, 1928-03-15 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - ALS Sir Edward Lutyens to Edward Knoblock, 1928-03-15; 215353
  - Ramsey MacDonald to Edward Knoblock, 1935-11-18 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - TLS Ramsey MacDonald to Edward Knoblock, 1935-11-18; 215352
  - Compton MacKenzie to Edward Knoblock, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - ALS Compton MacKenzie to Edward Knoblock, 1917-10-15; 215351
    - ALS Compton MacKenzie to Edward Knoblock, 1917-11-10; 215350
    - ALS Compton MacKenzie to Edward Knoblock, 1918-10-15; 215349
    - TLS Compton MacKenzie to Edward Knoblock, 1919-02-07; 215348
    - TLS Compton MacKenzie to Edward Knoblock (Missing), 1935-11-18; 215347
  - Eddie Marsh to Edward Knoblock, 1922-1931, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Undated, ALS Eddie Marsh to Edward Knoblock, 215346
    - ALS Eddie Marsh to Edward Knoblock, 1922-11-29; 215345
    - ALS Eddie Marsh to Edward Knoblock, 1922-05-08; 215344
    - ALS Eddie Marsh to Edward Knoblock, 1931-03-24; 215343
  - A.E.W. Mason to Edward Knoblock, 1934, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - ALS A.E.W. Mason to Edward Knoblock, 215342
    - ALS A.E.W. Mason to Edward Knoblock, 1934-08-13; 215341
    - ALS A.E.W. Mason to Edward Knoblock, 215340
    - ALS A.E.W. Mason to Edward Knoblock, 1934-12-20; 215339
  - Cyril Maude to Edward Knoblock, 1904-1911, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - ALS Cyril Maude to Edward Knoblock, 215338
    - ALS Cyril Maude to Edward Knoblock, 215337
    - ALS Cyril Maude to Edward Knoblock, 215336
    - ALS Cyril Maude to Edward Knoblock, 215335
    - ALS Cyril Maude to Edward Knoblock, 215334
    - ALS Cyril Maude to Edward Knoblock, 1904-09-22; 215333
    - TLS Cyril Maude to Edward Knoblock, 1908-12-29; 215332
    - TLS Cyril Maude to Edward Knoblock, 1911-03-07; 215331
  - Mary Moore to Edward Knoblock, 1910-01-01 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - ALS Mary Moore to Edward Knoblock An invitation to dinner and an apology for missing Knoblock earlier., 1 January 1910; 215330
  - Margot Oxford to Edward Knoblock, 1930-07-11, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Undated, ALS Margot Oxford to Edward Knoblock, 215329
    - Undated, ALS Margot Oxford to Edward Knoblock, 215328
    - ALS Margot Oxford to Edward Knoblock Dinner invite., 1930-07-11; 215327
  - Arthur Pinero to Edward Knoblock, 1916-1928 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - ALS Arthur Pinero to Edward Knoblock A note of thanks., 29 August 1916; 215326
    - ALS Arthur Pinero to Edward Knoblock, 1920-10-23; 215325
    - ACS Arthur Pinero to Edward Knoblock, 1921-02-20; 215324
    - ALS Arthur Pinero to Edward Knoblock, 1928-05-28; 215323
  - J.B. Priestley to Edward Knoblock, 1932, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - TLS J.B. Priestley to Edward Knoblock, 215322
    - TLS J.B. Priestley to Edward Knoblock, 1932-02-15; 215321
  - Edith Sitwell to Edward Knoblock (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Undated, ALS Edith Sitwell to Edward Knoblock Offering her opinions on Knoblock's novel The Ant Heap., 215320
  - George Sitwell to Edward Knoblock, 1930-08-10 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - ALS George Sitwell to Edward Knoblock, 1930-08-10; 215319
  - Osbert Sitwell to Edward Knoblock, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - TLS Osbert Sitwell to Edward Knoblock Asking if he can convert a book into a play., 1934-10-06; 215318
    - ALS Osbert Sitwell to Edward Knoblock, 5 January 1935; 215317
    - ALS Osbert Sitwell to Edward Knoblock, 4 March 1936; 215316
  - Sacheverell Sitwell to Edward Knoblock, 1930-08-14 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - ALS Sacheverell Sitwell to Edward Knoblock, 1930-08-14; 215315
  - Elanor Smith to Edward Knoblock (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Undated, ALS Eleanor Smith to Edward Knoblock, 215314
  - Herbert Tree to Edward Knoblock, 1914, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - ? ALS Herbert Tree to Edward Knoblock, 215312
    - ALS Herbert Tree to Edward Knoblock, 215311
    - TLS Herbert Tree to Edward Knoblock Also contains an incomplete letter in the hand of Tree, but not listed as a separate item., 1914-02-17; 215310
  - Lewis Waller to Edward Knoblock, 1912-07-08-1912-07-12 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - TLS Lewis Waller to Edward Knoblock, 1912-07-08; 215309
    - ALS Lewis Waller to Edward Knoblock, 1912-07-12; 215308
  - Hugh Walpole to Edward Knoblock, 1918-1925, Undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - ? ALS Hugh Walpole to Edward Knoblock, 215307
    - ALS Hugh Walpole to Edward Knoblock, 1918-06-02; 215306
    - ALS Hugh Walpole to Edward Knoblock, 1919-10-06; 215305
    - ALS Hugh Walpole to Edward Knoblock, 1925-07-27; 215304
    - ALS Hugh Walpole to Edward Knoblock, 1925-09-25; 215303
    - ALS Hugh Walpole to Edward Knoblock, 1919-05-14; 215302
    - ALS Hugh Walpole to Edward Knoblock, 1925-03-14; 215301
    - ALS Hugh Walpole to Edward Knoblock, 1923-03-11; 215300
  - Lord Wyndham to Edward Knoblock, 1911-1913, Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - ? C Lord Wyndham to Edward Knoblock, 215299
    - ? ALS Lord Wyndham to Edward Knoblock, 215298
    - ALS Lord Wyndham to Edward Knoblock, 1911-05-11; 215297
    - ALS Lord Wyndham to Edward Knoblock, 1913-02-05; 215296
  - Francis Brett Young to Edward Knoblocks, 1921-06-18 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - ALS Francis Brett Young to Edward Knoblock, 1921-06-18; 215295
  - Sir William Nicholson to Edward Knoblock, 1907-1936, Undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    General
    11 sketches/pictorial items sent by Nicholson to Knoblock at various times
  - Edward Knoblock Correspondence List (Box 1, Folder 46)